on this video I would like to share with
you an explanation that will make you
understand once and for all how llms
large language models like chat GPT work
I realized that the less we know about
AI the more magical it seems but when we
study and we learn more about it that
layer of magic and mystery goes away and
we end up realizing that it's a very
impressive technical accomplishment for
sure but that it is not magical or
intelligent at all this video and its
explanations are inspired by a great 1
hour and a half talk that I watched on
understanding AI given by the CTO of
Spotify which I recommend you watch if
you have the time because I know many of
you don't have the time to watch it I
decided to make this video where I'm
hoping to distill and summarize the talk
as much as possible so we can understand
on record time how chpt works from the
inside contrary to what you might think
understanding how chpt and other llms
work isn't that hard as you're about to
see conceptually is quite simple what is
hard is is the technical part turning
those Concepts into code which is the
topic for another very long video to
understand chpt and lm's conceptually
let's stop thinking of them as
intelligent beings let's instead think
of them as the autocomplete programs we
all use in our phones we can think of
chat GPT and llms as autocomplete
programs on steroids that we could
actually build ourselves manually if we
had enough time in a massive spreadsheet
let me explain if we were going to build
our own chat GPT manually what we would
have to do first is to make a
spreadsheet where we are going to put
all the words on the English dictionary
as the rose the Oxford dictionary has
around
170,000 words so we would end up with a
spreadsheet that looks something like
this for example to build our auto
complete the next step is to take all
the words in the dictionary and put them
all in a column each which is when our
Excel sheet is going to explode we would
end up with something like this as rows
we have every word in the dictionary and
as columns we also have every word in
the dictionary our Excel will have
170,000 rows and columns almost 29
billion cells our next goal would be to
calculate what is the probability that
the words in our vertical axis are
followed by the words in our horizontal
one to find those probabilities we would
have to read as many documents websites
comments papers and books as we can and
after a big effort we would end up with
something like this where now we can
tell with a high degree of probability
that for example the word apple is
followed by the word Tree in 90% of the
texts that we read or that ball is
followed by the word bounce 85% of the
cases but followed by the word barks
almost never okay we're doing great so
far but now we have a problem our
autocomplete only works with two words
we can autocomplete apple with tree and
Cat with chases or sun with shines but
what about a third word after apple tree
what comes next we need to also
autocomplete that to add support for a
third row we now have to add even more
rows to our already massive spreadsheet
and then calculate again what the
chances are for each word in the
dictionary to follow the two words Apple
Tre we would have to do this over and
over again for every set of two words
and then do it again for every set of
three words and so on and so on to be
able to autocomplete even longer
sentences as you can see conceptually
LMS are not that hard to understand what
is impressive is the technical
accomplishment on implementing an
architecture that can do what our
spreadsheet did but with thousands of
words as context that architecture is
called the Transformer and it was
introduced on a paper by Google
Engineers called attention is all you
need using this architecture the llm can
use thousands of words as context just
to guess what the next word is going
back to our spreadsheet that would be
like having a whole book in our word
column as context just to find out what
the last word of the last chapter of the
last sentence would be context is what
helps llms guess better that is why
people talk about prompt engineering the
more context that you give to an llm the
better it will perform think about it if
we give an llm a word like how there
will be many words that can follow it
with a high probability we could be
saying how are how many how come Etc but
if we give an llm the words how much is
there will not be as many options as
before now the words it that the will
have a higher probability and the words
him her and those will have lower
probabilities so the llm will choose how
much is it because it is the most common
across all the text it has seen But now
the question is if it's all about
probabilities there will always be a
word with the highest probability
doesn't that mean that the llm will
autocomplete the text always using the
same words how can llms be creative if
they are just a probability machine this
is when temperature comes in temperature
is like a lever on an llm that we can
increase or decrease temperature is what
makes chat G PT and llms appear like
they are created when the temperature of
the model is zero or close to it the
model will choose the words with the
highest probability to complete but as
the temperature goes up the model will
start to choose words that maybe have a
less probability but that still make
semantic sense so for example to
autocomplete the words I walk my the llm
will come up with a list of words and
its probabilities maybe dog will be the
highest followed by pet maybe followed
by dogs and so on since the temperature
is low the llm will go with the highest
probability and return I walk my top on
that list if dog pet and dogs were at
the top maybe cat iguana or cow are at
the bottom if we raise the temperature
the llm will make more random choices
and we'll start choosing words that are
on the list so they make sense but that
have a lower probability and this is how
the llm might return I walk my iguana
for example we know that the llm is a
massive autocomplete program trained on
the entire content of of the internet
the good and the bad included the last
piece of the puzzle is to understand how
we can turn this autocomplete program
into a question and answering machine
and give it the chatbot feeling also
since the program has seen the worst of
the internet how can we stop it from
giving harmful answers and make it stay
away from certain topics while being
helpful on others like chat refusing to
answer when asked how to make a bump the
chatbot part the way we can turn the
autocomplete into a question answer
machine is done by using something
called supervised fine tuning and here
is where humans come in to do supervised
fine tuning humans have to create a
bunch of documents that have the format
that humans want in the case of chat GPT
we can imagine an army of people and
thousands of documents that have the
question and answer format which is what
open AI wants for a chatbook the next
step is to train the autocomplete
machine a little bit more but this time
with the documents the humans prepare it
has already seen the entire internet but
now at the end of its training it will
only see documents with with the format
humans want this is called fine tuning
which is taking a model and training it
a bit more on some extra custom data the
last part is how to stop the llm from
giving harmful answers this is done by
using reinforcement learning with human
feedback which works like this after the
llm has been fine-tuned to become a
question and answering machine as we saw
before humans will now ask questions to
the llm and the llm will reply with five
answers to the question humans also
called labelers will rank those
responses from from best to worst if the
model gave harmful answers in the case
of Chip it makes sense to assume that
the labelers were instructed to rank
those harmful answers as the worst ones
labelers will do this lots and lots of
times until they have a big enough data
set and with this data set a reward
model will be trained the only job of
the reward model is to predict if a
response by the autocomplete will be
liked by a human or not and finally the
last step is to take the Wild uncensored
autocomplete question and answer machine
and train it again but this time against
the reward model the raw autocomplete
machine will get a question generate an
answer and ask the reward model if the
answer would be liked by a human or not
if the reward model says no it will have
to try again and again until it
understands what a good answer is and
learns that on its own the llm training
itself against the reward model can
happen lots and lots of times really
fast because it does not need human
intervention at all remember that by
default the model will be as crazy and
wild as the internet is using
reinforcement learning is how humans can
give values to the model and change its
political views censor it make it more
or less likely to talk about a certain
topic and so on that's it for this video
if you found it useful please like it
share it with your friends and subscribe
to the channel if you have time go and
watch the original talk it goes into
much more detail and talks about the
fusion models vectors and other
interesting stuff and remember that if
you want to learn to code for free with
me all you have to do is click the link
below there you will find free courses
on JavaScript python react react native
go Dart flutter and nextjs among many
others for absolutely free click the
link below and I will see you
there see you on the next one
bye-bye m